a few years ago you
uh posted a video
with the somewhat
tongue-in-cheek um
title how to enter first jhana jhana is
jhana is
often translated as
something that
that
can be entered upon
so
through a technique or meditation
method yeah
um
yeah so putting aside the
pali inaccuracies
um
could you expand on
why um
um
understanding entering upon ghana is
an accurate way of of understanding
china well no it's the implications of what
well no it's the implications of what
entering means that's what's inaccurate
that's why i said it took how to enter
ghana factually it wasn't like how to
enter jhana boom you can't enter it no
no you can enter it just not the way
that's commonly uh
presupposed yeah which is like i am
entering john which is like uh i'm doing
a meditation practice that then results
in a special experience that will be
jhana
and and also then kind of hand in hand
with that it's the assumption of
uh right i just go about my life and uh
if i commit to this like meditation
techniques and methods
i i still have
i could still experience and have access
to jhana without you know having
significantly uprooted sensuality centrality
uprooted sensuality centrality
unwholesome states dwelling restrained
uh you know with a gradual training and
virtue and all of that
so then it becomes like uh yeah like a
very kind of mystical type of esoteric
practice of
uh a special access to it thought by
this monk or that monk through this
method of that matter
but if you read the sutas given the jana
is from the sutas
you realize yeah sure there is a method
to jhana which is gradual training of
withdrawal from the senses seeing the
danger in the slightest fall being
watchful knowing your intentions not
acting out of greater version delusion
dwelling secluded and accomplished and
contemplating relinquishment also
left and right to everything that's
there to you then jhana will be
inevitable but see that's already not
nowhere near on the level of
techniques and methods that people would
assume or people are taught that china is on
or people are taught that china is on
so this idea of like a technique is in a
way uh it's affirming the wrong order that
uh it's affirming the wrong order that
yeah yeah
like is the
you will not be able to engage in a
technique without the wrong assumption yeah the
without the wrong assumption yeah the
wrong assumptions wrong order i wrong
view
in a way it is uh
it's like you're putting the hindrance
first this well you're acting out yeah
yeah you're acting out
which is i think i did another talk
johnny's a lifestyle or something like
that i think it was like um
john you don't enter john and john answers
you don't enter john and john answers
you no but yeah but there's also jhana
is a lifestyle all right
yeah yeah yeah i'm pretty sure there was
that one because it was exactly that you
realize oh you want to enter jhana your
entire lifestyle needs to be that
and that's why as i said in all of the
other talks on the giant playlist and so
on it's just
you see in the suttas it's always the
the pleasure of seclusion
from the unwholesome states
arises so you you experience the sense
of safety
from all the unwholesome things they use
to overwhelm you and control you
and then after that
you enter jhana the mind is composed in
that ghana
experience if you want to call it that
way but usually even that assumption
it's like no i entered jhana i entered
this special experience and then this
tremendous pleasure arises as a result
of that ghana because see first john is
pleasant no the withdrawal from unwholesome
no the withdrawal from unwholesome
states
is pleasant safety from unwholesome
states is pleasant and that's vagina is
not like i enter jhana and that pleasure
withdraws me from unwholesome states and
provides me with safety from wholesome
states that's upside down
so good another way of describing it be
um so you become established in
what the buddha would describe as
mindfulness and then you
um
you you direct that mindfulness
more particularly or more specifically
to like the first genre of the cessation
well it's i suppose in the broadest
terms they would be correct but again
you direct mindfulness
can easily be taken as okay so now i'm
doing this directional mindfulness for
the jhana no no
well your experience is fully purified
from the five hindrances
from the craving from the aversion from
the resisting of pain
from breaking of the virtue from
unwatchfulness from company
from company
that's it
you went to chance in a negative in that
negative way by not doing certain things
your mind gets established and
experienced that sense of safety on
account of unwholesome things that you
stopped being bound by and then you know
okay this is what jhana is
but if you think you can do something to
enter jhana in that sense
attend to this and i change that you're
just doing it again with your own
craving yeah so in that sense it's a
meditation with some central principle
not without
so that's why like the whole idea of
jhana being the meditation experience
should actually be completely abolished
like again as i said
it's not
in broader sense it's not wrong but in a
practical sense it always goes hand in
hand with all these extremely wrong
assumptions and mistakes
and mistakes
so it's it practically it's better and
safer to stop even regarding jhana as
any part of meditation experience and
focus on the gradual training of
withdrawal from unwholesome states
seeing the danger in the slightest fall
being watchful knowing your intentions
dwelling in seclusion
seeing the signs of your mind and then
john is the next thing
that you don't even have to want it will
have to happen if you develop everything
else rightly
i've had people ask um like that's why
sorry it's often
included as part of the gradual training towards
as part of the gradual training towards
enlightenment
in other words it's a neces it's like a
a next step they will come on its own if
you start developing gradual training
correctly the mind will be composed in the right
the mind will be composed in the right
manner the pleasure of safety will arise
in the right manner and you will know
that
i heard someone ask me like um they they
do these these 10-day silent retreats or
where they sort of sit in a hall
um
and they say like i have no intention of
speaking to anyone like it's like as if
i'm alone secluded alone secluded
um
could you describe why that isn't the
case why actually factually right you
need to be well the problem of that is
because it's it's a 10 day retreat so
what have you been doing before the
first day of the retreat and what are
you going to do after the 10th day of
the retreat
is your life like fully you know
celibate withdrawn from sensuality day
in day out
or is it just you know i'm trying my
best and then i go on a retreat when
everything is intense but then i go back
to my there's that uh
mahanima the the noble disciple layman
he occurs throughout majjimunika with
the buddha talking about various things
and there was that that sutra in the
buddha and
that imagined where he says how come the
noble disciple who has understood the
dharma clearly has seen the perils of
centrality sometimes still centrality
would come and you forget all the dhamma
you heard and the mind is just obsessed
with sexual desire and so on and then
the buddha says yeah well you know for
whoever has not experienced and
developed that pleasure differently the
pleasure of senses i pleasure of john on
account of the gradual training
their mind can still be attracted to
centrality in the in chinese agamas there is a
in the in chinese agamas there is a
parallel the same suture but actual
description with the buddha says whoever
hasn't experienced this
it's changed whereby it says
whoever still lives with his wives
and does not it's not basically celibate
enjoys the pleasure of sensuality
thought essentiality that's why you're
not experiencing the sensual uh pleasure
different from the senses and that kind
of ties in even better with another suit
i think in a good training i think i did
a talk on it
the one who doesn't see
danger gratification danger in the
escape in regard to sensuality the
entire sensuality that he can establish
his mind in the first gen such thing is
not possible
so you need to thoroughly withdraw
yourself through seeing the peril of
centrality and then jhana will come
but as i said more often than not
especially when it comes to the these
intense group retreats and so on the
idea is completely upside down
oh my life still very much revolves
around sensuality i cannot even fathom
or consider being completely celebrating
giving all the central joy that i get
from the world
but i'll just do these intense retreats
and get these quick access to these
these higher states they will then do
the work of renunciation for me
and that's just simply not how it works
the importance to recognize that it's
not an extension of a meditation technique
an extension of a meditation technique
it's not a special novelty experience
that arises it's quite the opposite the
unshakable mindfulness on account of
full withdrawal from sensuality because
you've seen the parallel of it
danger danger exactly and then you feel
you see if i recognize that i am
um well first of all if you recognize
the danger in itself don't want it that
you haven't been seeing before yeah that
in itself already offers your sense of
safety yeah cool wow this was so close
to me invisible all these years and now
i see it clearly and then you feel free
just just for that you will be relieved
yeah well i thought only now you pursue
that practice that goes even
further from that you know sensuality
they used to attract you yeah
and that is the safety is seeing the
danger because you don't want something
that's dangerous if you don't see it as
dangerous then
then you will just you'll be attracted
to it yeah yeah yeah
the poisonous drink in the similar
not not recognizing the poisons there
because it's not detectable to any of
the senses
you can't smell it you can't see it you
can't touch it you can't hear it you
can't taste it
and that's another problem of i think i
must have done a talk on that as well of
general meditation technique that's
concerned with observation
just a neutral you know like um
how they call that
non-engaging uh sort of
impersonal just observe anything that
comes and goes which again is the wrong
order well again you're observing that
with your personality yeah you can't
just assume the neutrality when your
experience is top to bottom taken as
mine i am
and personal
so so that's why like this whole
discernment of the poison becomes
impossible because poison is
undetectable through your senses it can
only be known once you've withdrawn from
the senses but here you are even your
meditation technique revolves around
furthering of your senses
catching every single moment between
your different observations
every single tactile sensation every
single thought every single side sound
smell there's touch touching feeling
sitting so observing yourself in the where the
so observing yourself in the where the
problem isn't even more
the eye can't see the eye yeah yeah the
thoughts can't access the mind
yeah so
so
so that's like the that peril the the
danger of centrality
needs to be discerned on that reflexive
level but if you still expect ghana
but if you still expect ghana
and liberation from all the unwholesome
states to come on the level of
technical and methodical observation
of like whatever side sounds mouth is
touches in case of sensations
the entire domain of knowledge is shut
you switch it up you're feeding the
hindrances which you're trying to escape
so it's like this yeah yeah it's still
very much within and sometimes people
might argue yeah but no see like you
know the suit has talked about this and
i still contemplate that all the super
contemplations and all the parallels
that you might draw from the suitors and
so on are secondary
to what you put first and what you put
first is observations of my senses
of touch sensations
sense of whatever sound smell
sound smell
taste sights
perceptions of my thoughts again all
based on assumptions that you have a
neutral access to them whereas in the
suit is the mindfulness that the order
that is encouraging is this yoni as in
the suitors exactly you don't need to be
observing every tactile sensation and
every sort of thought that passes
through your mind all you need to do is
sustain the context of not acting
towards the unwholesome ones not acting
out of it and you're the pressure
exactly and then if it's if it's not
unwholesome if it's not rooted in
pressure you can do it
and you realize that's what mindfulness
is
mindfulness is not
moment to moment watchfulness of every
second mindfulness is not acting out of
mindfulness is not acting out of
unwholesome states the context that's
developed in account of not acting out
of wholesome states is what
recollectness right memory correct
recollection and right context is and
also if all you are concerned with is
if all you are concerned with is
observing sensations or nostrils or
whatever technique you're doing
breathing in breathing our brain injury
the intention behind all those actions
is invisible to you because there has to
be a reason why you're doing those
things so
so
why is it that you're observing
sensations or trying to enter janna
through a technique why is that so
important to you
do you know that do you see that it's
not rooted in craving do to see that
it's not rooted in trying to
either avoid
or prolong the pleasure where is it due
to that
because it's obviously you know
if you look closely enough you realize
there is a degree of compassion there
there is a degree of no no no this is my
technique this is my method it's like
you know i've been doing this for so
long uh as like well see that's that's
uh as like well see that's that's
already um
very unsuitable basis for entering
if ghana
if there is craving involved if there is
pressure involvement there are
hindrances involved and if the hindrance
has evolved there is no such thing as
jhana there for you
that can be true i notice even
even if your technique is not as sort of
exactly you know proliferated proliferated as
you know proliferated proliferated as
those but you're still doing it with
that same attitude that you don't
recognize why you're even doing it yes
that's why that's what would have said
you know in jannah that that the
pleasure of jhana is not something you
can crave for
before or after or while you're in it
if there are no underlying tendencies
underline that
and that's why that pleasure is
wholesome
so you enter jhana by relinquishing
craving by relinquishing things you
crave for in which for most people who
learn jhana beforehand would be
relinquishing the idea of jhana
relinquishing the idea of meditation
technique leading to jhana that will
bring you closer to janna than doing the
technique towards jhana
and once yes the mind abides in such
relinquishing relinquishment
withdrawn from unwholesome states
uh in seclusion then as they would have
said yeah whatever like whether in that
state or first gen or second john and so on
or first gen or second john and so on
whether i
walk eat go to toilet extend my arm
whatever i do it's divine
it's it's outside of the domain of the
hindrances it's pure
and so you live in jhana you abide in
the john that's because you've
relinquished the body that is um
the necessary basis for all of the
hindrances so the hindrances
are affecting still affecting the body
but you've discerned it for example in
the first challenge
yes yeah
yeah and that obviously kind of you know
calls for redefining
uh
hindrances of statement hindrances
affect the body i know what you mean but
so
if you have not
surmounted the hindrances
your idea of hindrances affecting the
body would be very different than if you
have surmounted the hindrances and then
you can say yes you know hindrances
apply to the body but there's obviously
a very different level of how affected
the body is for somebody who's free from
hindrances and somebody who isn't
and that's where you know last talk we
talked about authenticity that's where
it comes in really like
seeing is this rooted in craving yeah
and it's like really being self-honest
you might
catch yourself and you realize okay this
is
this is rooted in craving you know i'm
here craving against these hindrances
in order to re-establish myself in ghana
which is why i'm within hindrances
because of my craving not because the
hindrances so now your record is that that doesn't
so now your record is that that doesn't
mean okay so i'll stop this no no i mean
it's like okay no i i detected the
mistake so all i should do now is still
strive to be free from hindrances just
minus my craving for being free from
and that's that brings to that whole you
know point that we often talk about oh
so then you learn how to endure it
rightly because if you endure it rightly
because if you endure it rightly
sufficiently enough you will be free
from it
it's your craving
while you're enduring things whether you
want to do not it's your craving that
interferes and obscures and
blurs that picture
so you might do things for decades but
if you endure with your craving that
you're unaware of that endurance will
not bear fruit
but if you recognize okay yeah endurance
is necessary however craving is not
necessary i can stop craving to to you know either
i can stop craving to to you know either
have janna or be free from this
unwholesome state i can just endure them
without acting out of by body speech and
mind and that's how you free yourself from
and that's how you free yourself from
hindrances and see that's not underlined
by craving now anymore
the result of that will be free from
craving and the result of that is china is the
is the
is that really like the simile of or the
analogy of addiction
being kind of freeing yourself from addiction
kind of freeing yourself from addiction
i don't is this is this a
a useful analogy like if you want to be
free from
the addiction of
addiction to cigarettes or whatever
it's not gonna work if you sort of
really just want the the end results of
kind of
you have to be sort of wanting to
actually do the work of
do the work of
um
not giving in to continually smoking
cigarettes as you can sort of expect to do
as you can sort of expect to do
something else that will then allow you
to not be yeah so
theoretically analogies is right because
it's yeah yeah it doesn't give you the
practically what the person needs to see
is like it's not enough
when it comes to insurance
to not just engage with centrality
physically like in case of cigarettes you need all
like in case of cigarettes you need all
you need to do is physically stop
smoking it and then the body will detox
itself and you will not crave for
cigarettes anymore now in case of
sensuality that same craving goes far
beyond body it's bodily of course
but it's it's rooted in your mind
so
you would need to not engage with the
body when it comes to sensuality you will
when it comes to sensuality you will
need to not engage with speech
but then you need to be enduring it on
the mental level
without acting out
uh towards it even by means of like
distraction and so on
and if you do it long enough on the
mental level without acting out
towards it one way or the other that's
how you will then uproot it in your mind
as well but what happens is people would
be withdrawn in the body in the speech
but then mentally they would feel
justified then in doing all sorts of
things including their practice because they
including their practice because they
don't want to deal with that pure pain
of saying no to centrality without
replacing it or covering it up
so that's what happens somebody like
becomes sense restraint and celibate and
then they start doing all this work and
projects and seemingly meaningful and
engaging and ideas and all of that to
keep themselves occupied and floating
because if they stop distracting
themselves in that engaging manner
externally wholesome manner well if they
stopped doing it then internally they
would feel the pain on that mantle and
that's what you need to feel
so that's what i mean like even
practicing the dharma doing things now
so to not deal with the pain is not the
dharma tama is on the level of enduring it and
tama is on the level of enduring it and
not distracting yourself from it
you can even like i don't know read a
suta about
freedom from sensuality or do a subasu
that's the common one i must do a subaru
i must do a subaru because i don't want
to endure the pain of this yes you must
do a suba but not at the expense of
enduring the the central uh pressure
and then exactly if you don't
habitually just try to get rid of that
pain of central and or of central
pressure and sensuality
you can do a super at any given time
within that sensuality and that's what
would have said
you would be able a monk who has
developed his mind correctly would be
able to see ugly within beautiful
or beautiful within ugly or ugly with an
ugly whatever permutation he sees it
right there as it is he wouldn't need to
engage in a set of motions techniques
and steps and you know
psychological methods to now replace
this sensuality with asuba because again
that's rooted in craving and craving is
the root of sensuality
so although you have nullified the
currently attractive object of
essentiality the whole framework of central pressure
the whole framework of central pressure
and pull and leaning towards those
objects remains unchanged
and that's exactly what happened to the
monks that did not develop yoni
somanasikara sufficiently and were
trying to do this asu but they ended up
being attracted to corpses and and so on
that suit is mentioned
so that's what i keep saying the most
important thing is
knowledge clarity honesty in regards to
the intentions behind your actions
whatever those actions might be body
speech or mind
so here we are i have a central pressure
what do you do oh let me
let me spend next six hours reading the
suitors and doing documentation why
it's not that it's bad but it's not good
either it depends on why you do it are
you doing it so you don't have to feel
the pain of sensuality or are you doing
it because you already saw the way out
of centrality and now you just want to
fortify that which one is it
do you think that just walking up and
down and reading the suitors will
magically give you a cure for sensuality
or do you just think oh no i just need
some more information to know how to do
this purely without resisting it taking
a screaming or trying to get rid of it
so your intention will determine whether
you're doing it rightly or not another
another
word i've heard you use
for intention is movement
and that's helped me in the past too
and also contemplate on the nature of
intention for example
for example
yeah i'm speaking to you now i might
have my i'm choosing to speak to you
um
so there is this sort of
intentional intention
um
and the reason why that is
yes i've used the word intentional
intention is because
that that choice is contained within
a broader
intention for example of my heart
beating my brain functioning my lungs
breathing that allow me to speak to you
right a necessary basis for you in
engaging moving along those intentions
so this yoni summoner sakai you talk
about um
yeah one way of sort of
of reflecting on one's intentions is
like i i are my intentions causing me to
ignore this broader context which
which um
helps me to understand that yeah
these inten these choices i'm making i i
don't own
point is like you to recognize like of
course you can't at the same time to the
same extent think about the you know
your current situation of beating heart
body here and intentions you're engaging
with they will take some attention
that's inevitable
but what is not inevitable is you losing
what is not inevitable is you losing
perspective
on account of choosing to act out of
those intentions and that's what you
recognize okay so like now you have a
intention to ask me a question
and then
yeah maybe that intention is rooted
because i'm restless or because i don't
want to be quiet or because i'm curious
or because i'm bored
or obviously in this case of course i
want to know
either of those ways will be engaging to
some extent
and but as long as you now know okay but see
but as long as you now know okay but see
if i'm if i am asking it because i want
to know
the answer can then shed more light for
the future practice in context so in
that case like pursuit of information is
wholesome because it can help you then eventually
because it can help you then eventually
stop depending on external information
because sometimes people kind of
you know get a sense of that but then
too soon they stop asking questions
because i mustn't ask questions that
would just be information and
intellectual knowledge well yeah you
need to know what you're supposed to do
either way you will be engaged and to
that extent you will lose perspective
but see this course of action loss of
perspective can then result in
broadening perspective later on because
now you know what to look for you will
know what to notice you might then
notice it
uh going a different course of action of
not asking questions or asking us for
wrong reasons and not paying attention
to it well again that's also distracting
itself but then in the future as well
will perpetuate
the distraction and it will not broaden
the context
so it comes down to yeah why why do i
like why they want to do this and often
like people
might be asking me questions on dhamma
but then they keep asking the same thing
every time we meet
and then it's obviously apparent to me
but it might not still be apparent to them
it might not still be apparent to them
that well you're not doing this for the
right reasons anymore you're just
repeating the same thing because you
need emotional conviction you need
emotional kind of
reassurance you are not merely seeking
information account of which to practice
you want me to reassure you
and that's not going to happen even if i
say things you want to to hear
it's your own mind that's making you
insecure and doubtful which means it's
going to last only for a period of time
before it comes back yeah
and so yes initially the questions might
have been rooted in really wanting to
learn but then that got obscured for
yourself and now your questions are
rooted just in
trying to rekindle that inspirational
kind of very wise words that you heard
externally using ears some kind of pair
of strengths
and like yeah you might do that it's not
necessarily immediate clear-cut but
sooner or later you will know clearly
what you're doing
and that's then when it comes down to
okay so now are you
consciously volitionally choosing to
perpetuate it or they're trying to put a
stop to it are you acting out of it
exactly are you acting out of it
and that's when when when when the kind
of choice of practicing the dharma is
brought back down onto you
because that is the opportunity of
seeing a nature yeah yeah that is the
opportunity of of like converging in the
right direction
and reinforcing the right direction and it's
and it's
entirely up to you that's the point
yeah it's not like oh i missed the
chance or i slipped it i didn't see this
no no it's always on the level of a very
conscious choice
that you when you become aware of it
decide to either ignore or do something
about it
this also brings me back to the
question i asked earlier on about
it's like sitting in a hall full of
people um because i used to do that a lot and
um because i used to do that a lot and
there was always this sense of
um
this might be a
bit off topic but this sense of there
being this collective responsibility oh
yeah we're doing this like you know
together oh you got to abandon that
long long before you even start that's
why seclusion is so important being
alone and yeah this is
individual responsibility but being
alone um mentally i think as well as in us
um mentally i think as well as in us
being alone with your own choices and
recognizing there is no collective group
here yeah yeah yeah
and even if you're sort of engaging with
somebody asking questions or yeah you
still realize where the emphasis is yeah
you have to be doing it ultimately in
order to be
not needing it yeah yeah but you kind of
end up wanting to what you described
that that often happens in the
monasteries as well monks develop this
notion we are in this together type of
thing and it's it's it's absolutely
laughable in a way like from the
authenticity point of view thinking we
are doing this together it's just what
like i was saying that in some other
context you know like the the assembly of
you know like the the assembly of
arahant it's not an assembly it's just a
group of individuals so it's an external
group of every single individual for
himself that's why it's the purest
assembly yeah there is no sense of
projected identity in the group
it's on the level of
inaudible oh it's easier for me to do
this if everybody else around me is
doing this
yeah that that can be a factual kind of
motive to start with fine sure get
reminded of what you're supposed to do
but if you don't see a problem with that
means you're never going to grow out of
it yeah means you will need then
everybody else to keep doing the same
thing so you keep your peace of mind
intact if one person steps out of the
line you will be existentially
challenged because it reminds you of the
fact that yeah we are all doing the same
now but at any given moment any given
person can choose to do the opposite
and that that means oh but then
i can choose to do the opposite
means i'm not in control of this you
know heavily controlled mind otherwise
and the environment and circumstances
and the rules and observances that we
all adhere to
and then there you go your piece went
out of the window
i'm the owner of my actions
along with my actions
there's nothing and no one can come between you
nothing and no one can come between you
and your actions